Joaquín de Alba Cartoon Collection 156
DCPL Special Collections - MLK Library
Joaquín de Alba Cartoon Collection
1966-1967
DCPL Special Collections - MLK Library
Alba, Joaquin de
156
2 Linear feet
1 Boxes
Arrangement
Series I: Drawings (.5 linear feet) The Drawings Series consists of sketches and caricatures of celebrities, U.S. politicians, and world leaders. Celebrities include George Hamilton and Bob Hope. Politicians include Gerald Ford, Lyndon B. Johnson, Adam Clayton Powell, and Henry Cabot Lodge. World Leaders include King Badouin of Belgium, Queen Elizabeth, and Fidel Castro. There are also courtroom sketches of the Bobby Baker Trial (1967) and the Robert Earl Barnes Trial. There are three "stories" which appear to be sketches for political cartoons: "Dog Story", "Long Hair Story", and "Private School Story". Folders are arranged alphabetically by the individual's last name. Series II: Plates The two plates are in separate small envelopes along with photocopies of the articles showing their publication in The Washington Daily News, February 27, 1967. One plate is an engraving of Gerald Ford; the other is Hervey Machen. Folders are arranged alphabetically by the individual's last name.
Biographical / Historical
Joaquin de Alba was born in Cadiz, Spain in 1912. He was an illustrator, painter, and political cartoonist who published his work under the pseudonym 'Kin' in Spain, and under his own name in the United States. His career as a political cartoonist began at the ABC newspaper of Seville, Spain in 1926, and he continued to work for various publications there until he left first for New York, and then later Washington, D.C. In 1966 he began working for The Washington Daily News. He eventually moved to Santo Domingo, Dominican Republic where de Alba was professor in the School of Fine Arts, which later became the National School of Visual Arts. He was nominated for a Pulitzer Prize in 1966 for his work. During Lyndon B. Johnson's presidency, he drew original cartoons for the Johnson Presidential Library and Museum in Austin, Texas. de Alba died in Palma del Rio, Spain in 1983.
Custodial History
No deed of gift has been identified. It is unclear how or when the Library acquired this collection.
Related Materials
Johnson Presidential Library and Museum in Austin, Texas. No collection name, or number identified.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of caricatures of politicians and world leaders, courtroom sketches, and two metal plates of two U.S. congressmen. The library holds 72 original political cartoons published in The Washington Daily News.
Politicians; Political cartoons; Politics and government; Drawings
- Series 1: Drawings, 1966-1967 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents
  The Drawings Series consists of sketches and caricatures of celebrities, U.S. politicians, and world leaders. Celebrities include George Hamilton and Bob Hope. Politicians include Gerald Ford, Lyndon B. Johnson, Adam Clayton Powell, and Henry Cabot Lodge. World Leaders include King Badouin of Belgium, Queen Elizabeth, and Fidel Castro. There are also courtroom sketches of the Bobby Baker Trial (1967) and the Robert Earl Barnes Trial. There are three "stories" which appear to be sketches for political cartoons: "Dog Story", "Long Hair Story", and "Private School Story". Folders are arranged alphabetically by the individual's last name.\
  - King Badouin of Belgium, 1967-03 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Jesse S. Baggett Board of County Commissioners, 1967-02 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Baker's Lawyers Boris Kostelanetz and Edward Bennett Williams, 1967-01 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Senator Alan Boyd, 1967-03 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Josip Broz (Tito), 1967-03 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Fidel Castro, 1966-10 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Ambassador Ellsworth Bunker, 1967-03 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - India Foreign Minister M.C. Chagla, 1967-03 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - [Maurice] Couve de Murville, 1966-12 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Thomas E. Dewey, 1966-12 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Anatoly F. Dobrynin, 1966-12 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Senator [Thomas Joseph] Dodd, 1967-02 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Dog Story, 1967-02 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Queen Elizabeth, 1967-02 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - "Ike" Dwight D. Eisenhower, 1966-01 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Representative Gerald Ford, 1966-02 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Senator J. William Fulbright, 1966-12 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Senator Ernest Gruening, 1967-03-01T00:00:00+00:00 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - George Hamilton, 1966-12-01T00:00:00+00:00 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Senator Carl Hayden (D., Nev.), 1967-01 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Senator Bourke Hickenlooper, 1967-03 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Bob Hope (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Lyndon B. Johnson, 1967-03 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Queen Juliana Netherlands, 1967-03 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Nicholas Katzenbach, 1966-12 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Kurt Kiesinger, 1967-02 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Henry Cabot Lodge, 1966-12 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Chief George J. Panagoulis, 1967-02 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Representative Wright Patman, 1967-02 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Adam Clayton Powell, 1967-01 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Representative L. Mendel Rivers (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - F. D. Roosevelt Jr., 1966-12 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Dean Rusk, 1966-12 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Arthur Schlesinger, 1967-02 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Former Representative Howard W. Smith, 1966-12 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Lord Snowdon, 1967-03 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Teng Hsiao Peng, 1967-02 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Juanita Thomas Robert G. (Bobby) Baker Case, 1967-01 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Mr. Ernest Tucker Bobby Baker Trial, 1967-01 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - General Earl Wheeler, 1966-12 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Senator John J. Williams (R., Del.), 1967-01 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Robert G. (Bobby) Baker Trial, 1967-01-14T00:00:00+00:00 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Robert Earl Barnes Trial, 1967-01 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - K. D. Childs, 1967-01 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Senator [Thomas Joseph] Dodd, 1967-03 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Lyndon B. Johnson, 1967-03 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Alexei Kosygin, 1967-02 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Long Hair Story, 1967-02 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Private School Story, 1967-03 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Sukharno, 1967-03 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Unnamed Trial, 1967-01 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Untitled sketch, 1967-03 (Box 1, Folder 54)
- Series 2: Plates, 1967 (Box 2)
  The two plates are in separate small envelopes along with photocopies of the articles showing their publication in The Washington Daily News, February 27, 1967. One plate is an engraving of Gerald Ford; the other is Hervey Machen. Folders are arranged alphabetically by the individual's last name.
  - Ford, Gerald, 1967-02 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Machen, Harvey, 1967-02 (Box 2, Folder 2)